<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>
          GPI Geospatial Inc.
        </origin>
        <pubdate>
          20191004
        </pubdate>
        <title>
          GPI_DEM_2018
        </title>
        <geoform>
          digital map
        </geoform>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>
        Bare-earth 5-foot DEM as 32-bit floating point raster format in ARCGIS GRID Raster format in
        compliance with USGS LIDAR Base Specifications such as: georeferencing information,
        delivered without overlap and with no edge artifacts or mismatched, “NODATA” value for void
        areas, bridges removed from the surface, etc.
      </abstract>
      <purpose>
        This is a Digital Elevation Model (DEM) as a raster mosaic in ESRI float format 32bit
        representation on a 5ft grid created from the LiDAR collected for the 2018_ITD_LiDAR project
        for the Miami-Dade County Information Technology Department (ITD). The DEM extent is
        Miami-Dade County as provided by ITD.
      </purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>
            20180425
          </begdate>
          <enddate>
            20181205
          </enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>
        ground condition
      </current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>
        COMPLETE
      </progress>
      <update>
        As needed
      </update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>
          -80.8825255556
        </westbc>
        <eastbc>
          -80.105244
        </eastbc>
        <northbc>
          26.0255653056
        </northbc>
        <southbc>
          25.2250032222
        </southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>
          none
        </themekt>
        <themekey>
          LiDAR
        </themekey>
        <themekey>
          METADATA
        </themekey>
        <themekey>
          DEM
        </themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>
          None
        </placekt>
        <placekey>
          Florida
        </placekey>
        <placekey>
          Miami-Dade
        </placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>
      None
    </accconst>
    <useconst>
      None. However, users should be aware that temporal changes may have occurred since this
      dataset was collected and that someparts of the data may no longer represent actual surface
      conditions. Users should not use the data for critical applications without a full awareness
      of the limitations of the data. The data was collected under the supervision of a Florida
      licensed Surveyor and Mapper in compliance with Florida Statute 472.000.
    </useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>
            GPI Geospatial Inc.
          </cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>
            mailing and physical
          </addrtype>
          <address>
            423 S Keller Road #300
          </address>
          <city>
            Orlando
          </city>
          <state>
            FL
          </state>
          <postal>
            32810
          </postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>
          407-851-7880
        </cntvoice>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>
      GPI Geospatial Inc.
    </datacred>
    <native>
      Microsoft Windows 10 pro; Esri ArcGIS 10.6.1.9270
    </native>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>
          GPI Geospatial Inc.
        </origin>
        <pubdate>
          20191004
        </pubdate>
        <title>
          GPI_DEM_2018
        </title>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>
        The LiDAR data was registered to ground control established by GPI Geospatial Inc. in 2018
        for the collection of LiDAR and Orthophotography of that year.This control is adequate to
        support the accuracy specifications identified for this project. The surveyor’s report
        documents and certify the procedures and accuracies of the horizontal and vertical control,
        aircraft positioning systems, and system calibration procedures used in this LiDAR mapping
        project. The horizontal and vertical control is based on direct ties to National Geodetic
        Survey (NGS) control stations, National Spatial Reference System (NSRS). The horizontal
        control references the North American Datum of 1983/2011current published datum
        (NAD_1983_2011_StatePlane_Florida_East_FIPS_0901_Feet). The vertical control references the
        NAVD88 using Geoid 12B to perform computations from ellipsoidal heights to orthometric
        heights. The vertical accuracy of the newly-established ground control is within one third
        of the specified LiDAR Fundamental Vertical Accuracy. All surveying &amp; mapping performed
        for this project meets or exceeds FEMA Flood Hazard Mapping Program, Guidelines and
        Specifications for Flood Hazard Mapping Partners, Appendix A, Section A.5 Ground Control,
        and Section A.6 Ground Surveys and as superseded by Procedure Memorandum No.61 – Standards
        for LiDAR and Other High Quality Digital Topography, 27 September 2010.GPI Geospatial Inc.
        collected the data at 20 points per square meter.
      </attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>
      See vendor's report
    </logic>
    <complete>
      Data set has been visually inspected. All data produced strives to meet National Mapping
      Accuracy Standards (NMAS).
    </complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>
          ASPRS does not require horizontal accuracy testing of LiDAR-derived elvation products.
        </horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>
          This product meets or exceeds the stated specifications for the state of Florida. The
          Vertical Accuracy for LiDAR data over well-defined surfaces was tested 0.204 feet vertical
          accuracy at 95 percent confidence level.as set forth in the FGDC Geospatial Positioning
          Accuracy Standards, Part 3: NSSDA. 65 check points were distributed throughout the project
          area.See vendor's report. North American Vertical Datum of 1988 (NAVD88).
        </vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>
              GPI Geospatial Inc.
            </origin>
            <pubdate>
              20191004
            </pubdate>
            <title>
              GPI_DEM_2018
            </title>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>
          digital
        </typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>
                20180425
              </begdate>
              <enddate>
                20181205
              </enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>
            ground condition
          </srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>
          Project Metadata
        </srccitea>
        <srccontr>
          GPI Geospatial Inc.
        </srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>
          The project was divided in two phases: Collection and classification of LiDAR data; and
          creation of 5-foot cell spaced hydro enforced mosaic DEM of the project area. The LiDAR
          data was collected utilizing a Riegl VQ-1560i in a Cessna 206 from an approximate altitude
          of 4,200 feet above ground level, at an approximate ground speed of 110 knots at a pulse
          rate repetition of 2000 kHg, resulting in an average of 15.2 points per square meter
          single swath and 20 plus with the 55% overlap. To get under the cloud celling some flight
          lines were collected at 2,000 feet agl at 110 knots. These lines were collected at 29.12
          points per square meter single swath. The sensor used a 60-degree field of view. The
          project was flown to have 55 percent overlap between swaths. The Global Positioning System
          (GPS) data were processed using Applanix POSPac Mapping Suite version 8.3 using Smart Base
          method and single base methods. A fixed bias carrier phase solution was computed in
          forward and reverse directions. The LiDAR collection took place when Positional Dilution
          of Precision (PDOP) was at or below 3. Occasionally, the PDOP rose slightly above 3. This
          had no effect on the data. The GPS trajectory was combined with the IMU data using the
          Applanix POSPac software. The resulting Smoothed Best Estimate of Trajectory (SBET) was
          exported and used in Riegl RiProcess software to compute the laser mass point positions in
          Northing, Easting, and Elevations coordinates.The raw laser data were merged with the SBET
          using Riegl RiProcess software. The data set was processed using RiProcess, RiAnalyze, and
          RiWorld software where each flight line was processed to a point cloud. The data was
          adjusted flight line to flight line using Riegl’s Scan Data Adjustment tool to ensure a
          proper relative calibration match between flight lines. Each flight was checked for
          project coverage, data gaps between overlapping flight lines, point density and then
          exported in LAS 1.4 format. The entire project was collected without gaps. The LAS files
          were projected to the NAD_1983_2011_StatePlane_Florida_East_FIPS_0901_Feet and North
          American Vertical Datum of 1988 (NAVD88). Ellipsoidal heights were converted to
          orthometric heights using the current Geiod12B. The LAS files were imported to TerraSolid,
          LTD TerraScan software to be classified to bare earth ground and later feature coded to
          USGS specifications. The LAS files contain 12 classifications: 1 = unclassified; 2 =
          ground; 3 = low veg; 4 = med veg; 5 = high veg; 6 = building; 7 = noise points; 9 = water;
          10 = buffered ground points surrounding breaklines; 12 = overlap; 17 = overpass and
          bridges; 18 = high noise. The LiDAR data was run through an automated ground and building
          classification using terrascan software. A manual check of the building classification was
          done. The vegetation heights were assigned by an automated process after the bare-earth
          and buildings were classified. No manual classification of the vegetation class was
          performed on this data set. Breaklines were digitized from the LiDAR data in Microstation
          and elevations were assigned using LP360 and ArcGIS. The double line linear hydrographic
          features were hydro-enforced with downhill constraints to model correct flow patterns.
          Water bodies were hydro-flattened to ensure uniform elevation across the feature. DEMs
          were created using QCoherent LP360 software. The bare-earth LAS data was loaded into the
          software along with the tile layout and hydro shapefile collected from the LAS data set.
          DEMS were produced at a 5ft cell size and hydro-flattened. To QC the DEMs Global Mapper
          was used to check for completeness of the tiles and that the hydro features were flattened
          and represented correct elevations. Once the QC was complete the files were exported out
          of ArcGIS to create Arc DEM. COLLECTION DATES: 4/25/18, 4/26/18, 4/29/18, 4/30/18,
          5/01/18, 6/05/18, 6/06/18, 6/22/18, 12/05/18173 flight lines of data were collected.
        </procdesc>
        <procdate>
          2018
        </procdate>
        <proccont>
          <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
              <cntorg>
                GPI Geospatial Inc.
              </cntorg>
              <cntper>
                Iarelis D. Hall, PSM
              </cntper>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntpos>
              Assistant Vice President of Surveying and Mapping Operations of South Florida
            </cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
              <addrtype>
                mailing and physical
              </addrtype>
              <address>
                423 S Keller Rd Suite #300
              </address>
              <city>
                Orlando
              </city>
              <state>
                Florida
              </state>
              <postal>
                32810
              </postal>
              <country>
                US
              </country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>
              407-937-1522
            </cntvoice>
            <cntemail>
              ihall@gpinet.com
            </cntemail>
            <hours>
              0800 - 1700
            </hours>
          </cntinfo>
        </proccont>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>
      Vector
    </direct>
    <ptvctinf>
      <sdtsterm>
        <sdtstype>
          Entity point
        </sdtstype>
        <ptvctcnt>
          1
        </ptvctcnt>
      </sdtsterm>
    </ptvctinf>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <mapproj>
          <mapprojn>
            Transverse Mercator
          </mapprojn>
          <transmer>
            <sfctrmer>
              0.99994118
            </sfctrmer>
            <longcm>
              -81
            </longcm>
            <latprjo>
              24.33333333333333
            </latprjo>
            <feast>
              656166.6666666665
            </feast>
            <fnorth>
              0.0
            </fnorth>
          </transmer>
        </mapproj>
        <planci>
          <plance>
            coordinate pair
          </plance>
          <coordrep>
            <absres>
              0.00032808333333333333
            </absres>
            <ordres>
              0.00032808333333333333
            </ordres>
          </coordrep>
          <plandu>
            US FEET
          </plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>
          North American 1983 (2011)
        </horizdn>
        <ellips>
          GRS 1980
        </ellips>
        <semiaxis>
          6378137.0
        </semiaxis>
        <denflat>
          298.257222101
        </denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>
          dem_5ft
        </enttypl>
        <enttypd>
          DEM raster dataset for Miami-Dade County* Pixel depth 32* Compression type None* Number of
          bands 1* Raster format GRID* Source type continuous* Pixel type floating point
        </enttypd>
        <enttypds>2018 LiDAR data collected by GPI Geospatial Inc. model keys.</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>Miami-Dade County Information Technology Department (ITD)</cntorg>
          <cntper>Mapping &amp; GIS</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>5680 SW 87th Avenue</address>
          <city>Miami</city>
          <state>FL</state>
          <postal>33173</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>305-596-8398</cntvoice>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <resdesc>Data are available from ITD on a request basis. Raster Dataset</resdesc>
    <distliab>Translation of files to formats other than those described here is the sole responsibility of individuals downloading the data.</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <digform>
        <digtinfo>
          <formname>raster dataset</formname>
        </digtinfo>
        <digtopt>
          <offoptn>
            <offmedia>Digital</offmedia>
            <recfmt>Digital</recfmt>
          </offoptn>
        </digtopt>
      </digform>
      <fees>Miami-Dade County offers the imagery free of charge; cost is associated to reproduction time and materials.</fees>
      <ordering>Contact Mapping and GIS</ordering>
    </stdorder>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20191004</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>GPI Geospatial Inc.</cntorg>
          <cntper>Iarelis D. Hall, PSM</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntpos>Assistant Vice President</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>423 S Keller Rd. #300</addrtype>
          <city>Orlando</city>
          <state>FL</state>
          <postal>32810</postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>407-937-1522</cntvoice>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
    <mettc>local time</mettc>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>
